A Guide to the Papers of Hugh Scott, 1941-1983
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Hugh Scott 1941-1983
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10200-n, -p
This collection consists of ca. 7500 items (15 Hollinger boxes, ca. 6.25 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The additions to the Hugh Scott Papers were a gift to the University of Virginia Library of the Honorable Hugh Scott of Washington, D.C., and includes 10,200-n, given on February 4, 1982 and 10,200-p, given on October 12, 1982.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the Hugh Scott Papers consists of ca. 7500 items (15 Hollinger boxes, ca. 6.25 linear shelf feet), 1941-1983, of his naval service papers and political papers, including minority leader files, photographs, and memorabilia chiefly concerning Scott's career as a United States senator.
The naval service papers, 1941, 1945, and 1969, are comprised of material concerning Scott's work in communications for the 3rd amphibious force. There are official orders and public information plans mainly concerned with the surrender of Japanese public information personnel and the occupation of Japan.
The political papers include material on Richard M. Nixon's resignation as president of the United States, including meetings with Mike Mansfield on impeachment procedure, Scott's trips to China and the Soviet Union, and his retirement from the Senate. In the Chinese trips papers are transcripts of talks, 1976, with Vice Premier Chang Ch'un Ch'iao and foreign minister Ch'iao Kuan-hu, and notes for an interview, 1972, with Chou En-lai.
There is also a VIP file which includes letters signed by Spiro T. Agnew, George Bush, John Connally, Thomas E. Dewey, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Mamie Eisenhower, Gerald R. Ford, King Hussein, Lyndon B. Johnson, Lady Bird Johnson, John F. Kennedy, Robert F. Kennedy, Henry A. Kissinger, Alf M. Landon, Henry Cabot Lodge, Robert S. McNamara, Richard M. Nixon, Eugene Ormandy, Cliff Robertson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, William P. Rogers, George Romney, Dean Rusk, and William W. Scranton. Other prominent correspondents in the political papers include Sam Ervin, Leon Jaworski and Mike Mansfield. There are also brief notes from several senators on Scott's proposed retirement.
The senatorial papers consist of minority leader files. This material includes statements from Mike Mansfield and Scott, notes from leadership meetings with the president, vice-president, cabinet, Senate, and House leaders' files re various campaigns, and a "201" file (A military phrase meaning a personal or individual file.) containing correspondence with Scott's Republican colleagues, with a separate folder for each. There is also correspondence with Democratic senators including Birch Bayh, Philip A. Hart, Hubert H. Humphrey, Edward M. Kennedy, Walter F. Mondale, Edmund S. Muskie, William Proxmire, Adlai E. Stevenson, and John V. Tunney.
The photographs, 1968-1976, are chiefly of Republican senators during certain political events, such as Nelson A. Rockefeller's announcement of his candidacy in 1968, the resignation of Richard M. Nixon in 1974, and Gerald R. Ford and Nelson A. Rockefeller being sworn in as president and vice-president.
Senators and other prominent politicians pictured include Wallace F. Bennett, Robert C. Byrd, Gerald R. Ford, Jake Garn, Robert P. Griffin, Clifford P. Hansen, Edward M. Kennedy, Mike Mansfield, Frank Moss, Richard Nixon, Nelson A. Rockefeller, and Hugh Scott. There are also photographs of Hugh and Marian Scott's trips to China in 1972 and 1976, and one of Leonid I. Brezhnev.
Organization
The material had been arranged topically by Hugh Scott's staff; the original order and titles and descriptions have been retained with some modifications. The papers are organized in the following series: I. Naval Service Papers, II. Political Papers, III. Congressional Papers, IV. Photographs, V. Miscellaneous, and VI. Oversize. Folders within the series are arranged alphabetically with the exception of those in the photographs and miscellaneous series, which are arranged chronologically, series II and III divided into several sub-series.
Contents List
- I. Naval Service Papers
  - Naval Service: Correspondence 1945 Aug. -Oct. (Box 1)
  - Naval Service: Miscellaneous 1941, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Naval Service: P.I.O. Surrender and Occupation of Japan 1945 Aug.-Sept. (Box 1)
  - Naval Service: Public Information Plans 1945 July-Aug. (Box 1)
- II. Political Papers-General
  - A: General
    - Bicentennial Celebration 1976 July 4, 6 (Box 1)
    - Ford Administration 1974 Aug. -Oct. (Box 1)
    - Greeting cards, Invitations 1962-1965 (Box 1)
    - Nixon Resignation 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Nixon Resignation 1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Retirement Announcement 1975 (Box 2)
    - Retirement, Letters regarding 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - B: VIP File
    - "A" VIP 1953, 1967-1976 (Box 3)
    - Spiro T. Agnew 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    - "B" VIP 1950, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - "C" VIP 1965-1976 (Box 3)
    - "D" VIP 1960-1974 (Box 3)
    - Dwight D. Eisenhower 1952-1969 (Box 3)
    - Mamie Eisenhower 1965-1974 (Box 3)
    - "F" VIP 1968-1976 (Box 3)
    - Gerald R. Ford 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - "G" VIP 1970, 1974 (Box 3)
    - "H" VIP 1970-1975 (Box 3)
    - "I" VIP 1974 (Box 3)
    - "J" VIP 1965-1975 (Box 3)
    - Lyndon B. Johnson 1959-1973 (Box 3)
    - "K" VIP 1964-1975 (Box 3)
    - John F. Kennedy 1960, 1963, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Henry A. Kissinger 1970-1975 (Box 3)
    - "L" VIP 1960-1975 (Box 3)
    - Alf M. Landon 1962-1976 (Box 3)
    - "Mc" VIP 1967-1974 (Box 3)
    - "M" VIP 1953, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
    - Richard M. Nixon 1955-1974 (Box 3)
    - Richard M. Nixon 1955-1974 (Box 4)
    - "O" VIP 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    - "P" VIP 1968-1976 (Box 4)
    - "R" VIP 1963-1976 (Box 4)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller 1960-1976 (Box 4)
    - "S" VIP 1959, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
    - William W. Scranton 1962-1969 (Box 4)
    - "T" VIP 1970-1973 (Box 4)
    - "V" VIP 1970-1975 (Box 4)
    - "W" VIP 1969-1975 (Box 4)
    - "Y" VIP 1968 (Box 4)
  - C: Trips
    - China Trip: Preparations 1972 Mar.-Apr. (Box 4)
    - China Trip: in China 1972 Apr.-May (Box 4)
    - China Trip: Miscellaneous 1972 Apr.-June (Box 4)
    - China Trip: Post Trip Reports and Interviews 1972 May-July (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Preparations 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - China Trip: in China 1976 Mar.-July (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Newspaper Articles 1976 June-Aug. (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Background Information 1976 July (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Report to President Ford 1976 July (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Transcripts of Meetings with Chang Ch'un-ch'iao and Ch'iao Kuan-hua 1976 July (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Post Trip 1976 July-Sept. (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Draft of Report to Senate 1976 Aug., 2 folders (Box 5)
    - China Trip: Report of Pat Holt's Trip 1976 Aug. (Box 6)
    - China Trip: Television shows with Charles Freeman re trip 1976 Sept. (Box 6)
    - China Trips: Printed 1971-1976 (Box 6)
    - Soviet-U.S. Parliamentary Exchange 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Soviet-U.S. Parliamentary Exchange: Meeting with Brezhnev 1974 (Box 6)
- III: Congressional Papers
  - A: Minority Leader Files: correspondence and papers
    - Agnew, Vice President Spiro T. 1973 (Box 6)
    - Agnew, Vice President Spiro T., resignation of 1973 (Box 6)
    - Democratic Conference, including Senator Mike Mansfield's statements as head 1969-1976 (Box 6)
    - Democratic Senators 1963-1976 (Box 6)
    - Gerald R. Ford 1971-1976 (Box 6)
    - Mansfield, Senator Mike 1969-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Republican Leader Messages, Letters, etc. to Members 1970-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Rockefeller, Vice President Nelson A. 1973-1975 (Box 7)
    - Scott-Mansfield, Joint Letters, Messages, Statements, etc. 1969-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Witonski, Peter 1975 (Box 7)
  - B: Minority Leader Files: Leadership notes of meetings
    - Leadership Notes of Meetings 1969-1974, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Leadership Notes of Meetings 1975-1976, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - C: Minority Leader Files: Campaigns
    - Article re Germond Article 1975 (Box 9)
    - Chairmanship-Republican Senatorial Campaign Committee 1965-1967 (Box 9)
    - Judiciary-Supreme Court 1970-1971 (Box 9)
    - Kissinger Nomination 1973-1974 (Box 9)
    - Kissinger Investigation 1974 (Box 9)
    - Minority Leadership Election 1974 (Box 9)
    - Minority Leadership Race 1969 (Box 10)
    - Minority Leadership Race 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Minority Leadership Race 1971-1972 (Box 10)
    - National Committee for an Effective Congress 1966 (Box 10)
    - Pennsylvania Senate Campaign 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - Presidential Campaign 1966-1968, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Presidential Campaign 1971-1972 (Box 10)
    - Presidential Campaign 1974-1976 (Box 11)
    - Republican National Convention 1971-1972 (Box 11)
    - Republican National Convention: Rules Changes 1972 (Box 11)
    - The Ripon Society, From Disaster to Distinction1966 (Box 11)
    - Senate Campaigns 1970 (Box 11)
    - Senate Campaigns 1972 (Box 11)
    - Senate Campaigns 1973-1974 (Box 11)
    - Senate, Scott Campaign 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    - Whip Race 1969 (Box 11)
  - D: Minority Leader Files: "201" file for Republican colleagues
    - George D. Aiken 1970-1974 (Box 12)
    - Gordon Allott 1970-1972 (Box 12)
    - Howard H. Baker, Jr. 1969-1976 (Box 12)
    - Dewey F. Bartlett 1972-1976 (Box 12)
    - J. Glenn Beall, Jr. 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Henry Bellmon 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Wallace F. Bennett 1969-1974 (Box 12)
    - J. Caleb Boggs 1970-1974 (Box 12)
    - W. E. Brock 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Edward W. Brooke 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - James Buckley 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Clifford P. Case 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Marlow W. Cook 1970-1974 (Box 12)
    - John Sherman Cooper 1970-1975 (Box 12)
    - Norris Cotton 1970-1975 (Box 12)
    - Carl T. Curtis 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Robert J. Dole 1970-1976 (Box 12)
    - Peter V. Domenici 1972-1976 (Box 12)
    - Peter H. Dominick 1970-1974 (Box 12)
    - Paul J. Fannin 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - Hiram L. Fong 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - Jake Garn 1974-1976 (Box 13)
    - Charles E. Goodell 1970 (Box 13)
    - Barry M. Goldwater 1963-1976 (Box 13)
    - Robert P. Griffin 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - Edward J. Gurney 1970-1974 (Box 13)
    - Clifford P. Hansen 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - Mark O. Hatfield 1966-1976 (Box 13)
    - Jesse Helms 1972-1976 (Box 13)
    - Roman L. Hruska 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - Jacob K. Javits 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - Len B. Jordan 1969-1972 (Box 13)
    - Paul Laxalt 1974-1976 (Box 13)
    - Charles McC. Mathias, Jr. 1970-1976 (Box 13)
    - James A. McClure 1972-1976 (Box 13)
    - Jack R. Miller 1970-1974 (Box 13)
    - Thruston B. Morton 1975 (Box 13)
    - Karl E. Mundt 1970-1972 (Box 13)
    - George Murphy 1970 (Box 13)
    - Robert W. Packwood 1969-1976 (Box 14)
    - James B. Pearson 1969-1976 (Box 14)
    - Charles H. Percy 1969-1976 (Box 14)
    - Winston L. Prouty 1970-1971 (Box 14)
    - William V. Roth 1969-1976 (Box 14)
    - William B. Saxbe 1970-1975 (Box 14)
    - Richard S. Schweiker 1970-1976 (Box 14)
    - William L. Scott 1972-1976 (Box 14)
    - Hugh Scott with Robert C. Byrd, Mike Mansfield, and Robert P. Griffin, in a meeting re Richard M. Nixon's resignation 1974 July 29 (Box 15)
    - Meeting of Republican Senators, including Hugh Scott, re Richard M. Nixon's resignation 1974 Aug. 7 (Box 15)
    - Gerald R. Ford in the House three days after being sworn in as President 1974 Aug. 12 (Box 15)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller: Confirmation Vote 1974 Dec. 10 (Box 15)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller: Swearing-in of the Vice-President 1974 Dec. 19 (Box 15)
    - Hugh Scott, Frank Moss, Jake Garn, and Wallace Bennett 1974 Dec. (Box 15)
    - Hugh and Marian Scott; Vice Premier Chang Ch'un-ch'iao; Foreign Minister Ch'iao Kuan-hua; Chou-Pei-yuan, Vice Premier of the Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs; Robert Barnett; Charles W. Freeman; others in China 1976 July 10-24 (Box 15)
    - Senate Resolution to name the Philip A. Hart Office Building 1976 Sept. (Box 15)
- V. Miscellaneous
  - Passports 1949-1972 (Box 15)
  - Printed, The Sam Rayburn Library Newsletter 1982 Jan. 6 (Box 15)
  - Printed, Miscellaneous 1983 (Box 15)
- VI. Oversize-Photographs
  - Leadership Meeting with Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, Hugh Scott, and others [1971 Aug.] (Box 15)
  - China Trip preparations, Henry Kissinger, Mike Mansfield, Richard Nixon, and Hugh Scott 1972 Apr. (Box 15)